A Finding Aid to the Reginald R. Isaacs Papers, circa 1842-1991, bulk 1928-1991, in the Archives of American Art AAA.isaaregi
Archives of American Art
- Walter Gropius Biography, circa 1800s-1991, undated; Series 13; 16 Linear feet Boxes 6-22, OV 23, MGP 1, 2, 4
  - Research and Bibliographic Material, circa 1883-1986, undated; 13.2
    - Faquswerk - Feuchtwanger (Box 7, Folder 81)
      Includes Feininger, Lyonel, 1959, 1968 - essay "Address on the Artist."
    - Field - Fitch (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - Fletcher - Frank (Box 7, Folder 83)
      Includes Florence, Philip Sargent correspondence with Jack C. Pritchard, 1936-1937, 1966; Forberg, Sarina Elisabeth, 1975.
    - Frankfurt, Germany, 1948, 1962-1964 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Concerns proposed planning procedure for Frankfutam-Main to be the Capitol of West Germany; two plats relating to Am Lindenbaum Development competition housed in OV 23.
    - Free University, Berlin - Friedrich (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Fry, E. Maxwell, and Jane Drew, 1937-1984 (Box 8, Folder 3-5)
    - Furniture, 1972-1985 (Box 8, Folder 6-9)
      About furniture designed by Gropius including correspondence with Ise Gropius and Hans Wingler, and photographs and appraisals of furniture.
    - Galbraith - Gibbard (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Giedion, Sigfried, 1933-1965, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
    - Gilbert - God is in the Details (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Goethe Prize, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Gonzalez-Reyna - Griswold (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Gropius, Ise, 1911-1967 (Box 8, Folder 16-19)
      Includes biographical material, notes, and excerpts from her correspondence.
    - Gropius, Walter, 1906-1974 (Box 8, Folder 20-44)
      Includes biographical material, genealogy material, and notes and writings by and about Gropius.
    - Gropius House History, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Gropp - Gummere (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Hamm - Hannoversche Papiefabriken Alfeld-Gronau (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Hardt - Hartmann (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Harvard University, 1920-1983 (Box 8, Folder 49-71)
      Material about the Departments of Architecture, Landscape Architecture, Regional Planning, and the Graduate School of Design including correspondence with Walter Bogner, John T. Boyd, Jr., Joseph B. Conant, Richard Filipowski, Henry A. Frost, Henry Hubbard, Joseph Hudnut, Charles Killam, Henry A. Kissinger, Warren P. Laird, Bremer Pond, Jerzy Solton, and Jaqueline Tyrwhitt.
    - Harvard University, cont. (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Harvard University, Visiting Committee, 1962-1968 (Box 9, Folder 5-8)
      About the Graduate School of Design and Visual Arts.
    - Hassenpflug - Hess (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Includes Hebebrand, Werner, 1951, 1956, 1963.
    - Hesse - Hildebrandt, Hans (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Hildebrandt, Lily, 1919-1984 (Box 9, Folder 11-14)
      Includes excerpts of letters between Gropius and Hildebrandt translated by Ise Gropius; correspondence with Isaacs and Rainer Hildebrandt; and photographs of Hildebrandt, and her works of art.
    - Hildebrandt, Rainer - Hillebrecht, Rudolf, 1948-1974 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Hinder - Holden (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Holford, Sir William, 1960, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Hollatz - Honig (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Hopp - Hoyt (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Hudnut, Joseph, 1929, 1934-1952, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 20-44)
      Includes correspondence with Charles A. Coolidge, John M. Gaus, Henry James, Charles D. Maginnis, Elbert Peets, Leverett Saltonstall, Henry R. Shepley, regarding the arrival of Walter and Ise Gropius to Harvard University, and the Department of City and Regional Planning.
    - Huffner - Hutcheon (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Huter, Karl-Heinz, 1964-1975, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - Huxley, Aldous (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - Implington Village College, Cambridge, England (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Integrity (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Interbau Bilderdienst, 1956, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Institute of Design, Chicago, 1939-1955 (Box 9, Folder 51-54)
      Includes correspondence with Charles Eames, Sigfried Giedion, Nathaniel H. Owings, Walter Paepcke, and Ludwig Mies van der Rohe.
    - Iraq, University of Baghdad - Janos (Box 9, Folder 55)
      Includes Itten, Johannes, 1964-1965.
    - Japan, 1953-1985 (Box 9, Folder 56-61)
      About Walter and Ise Gropius' travels.
    - Jefferson National Expansion Memorial Architectural Competition, St. Louis, Missouri, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 62-63)
    - Jenney - Joedicke (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - John F. Kennedy Federal Building, 1963-1969 (Box 9, Folder 65-68)
      Includes correspondence with Herbert Ferber, Dimitri Hadzi, and Robert Motherwell.
    - Johnson - Kagan (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - Kandinsky - "Kapp Putsch" (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Includes Kapp Putsch memorial commission, 1968 with photograph of Emauel Dion.
    - Karbe, Klaus, 1964-1983 (Box 10, Folder 2-5)
    - Karlsruhe, Dammerstock - Klopfer (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Includes Klee, Paul, 1921, 1926; and Klee, Felix Paul, 1966, 1967.
    - Koch - Kokoschka (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Konig, Heinrich, 1928, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Korn, Arthur, 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Kramer - Kusmirek (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Lanier - Le Corbeiller (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Le Corbusier, 1952-1965 (Box 10, Folder 12-14)
      Includes correspondence with Lucio Costa and Jose Luis Sert.
    - Lectures by Walter Gropius, 1932-1934 (Box 10, Folder 15-21)
      Includes correspondence with Farkas Molnar, Maxwell Fry, Sigfried Giedion, and Erich Mendelsohn.
    - Leiteritz - Linde (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Literature-Publications Which Influenced Gropius (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Lock - Lynch (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - London, England, 1934-1983 (Box 10, Folder 25-38)
      Information about the Park Lane Building Commission, Piccadilly Circus project and the Pioneer Health Center, correspondence with Ronald Coleman, Jack Cotton, Richard Llewelyn Davies, Sir William Holford, and Jack Pritchard.
    - Mackay-Lewis - Maginnis (Box 10, Folder 39)
      Includes Maginnis, Charles, 1951-1952.
    - Mahler, Alma, circa 1910-1920 (Box 10, Folder 40-47)
      Includes Ise Gropius' translations of letters between Walter and Alma.
    - Maldonado - Manchester, England, A.P. Simon Housing Development (Box 10, Folder 48)
      Plat housed in OV 23.
    - Mandroti - Markische Viertel (Box 10, Folder 49)
    - Modern Architectural Research (MARS) Group, 1937-1938, 1947-1955 (Box 10, Folder 50-52)
      Includes correspondence with Wells Coates, Jane Drew, Sir William Holford, and Jacqueline Tyrwhitt, meeting minutes and membership information.
    - Martin - McCullough (Box 10, Folder 53)
    - McGrath - Mendizabal (Box 10, Folder 54)
    - Meyer, Hannes, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 55)
    - Mickin, Margaret and Walter, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 56)
    - Miller - Molnar (Box 10, Folder 57)
    - Moholy-Nagy, Laszlo and Sibyl, 1937-1949 (Box 10, Folder 58-67)
      About the formation of the "New Bauhaus," the Institute of Design, includes correspondence with Alexander Archipenko, Sewell Avery, Sibyl Moholy-Nagy, Richard Neutra, Walter Paepcke, and Xanti Schawinsky.
    - Morgan - Muller-Boehat (Box 10, Folder 68)
    - Mumford - Muthesius (Box 10, Folder 69)
      Includes Mumford, Lewis, 1940, 1946.
    - Nachtigal - Neufert (Box 10, Folder 70)
      Includes National Broadcasting Co., Inc., 1957 about Gropius' appearance on NBC's "Wisdom Series, Conversation with Walter Gropius."
    - Neumann - Norton (Box 10, Folder 71)
      Includes Neutra, Richard, 1951, 1968.
    - O'Connor - Osthaus (Box 10, Folder 72)
    - Otto - Owers (Box 10, Folder 73)
    - Paepcke, Walter, 1944-1945 (Box 10, Folder 74)
    - Pan American Building, 1962-1983 (Box 10, Folder 75-78)
    - Pankok - Paulssen, van Lunaeboerg (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Peht - Plimpton (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Poland (Box 11, Folder 3-5)
    - Political Activities, 1946, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      About the United Nations building site and the Mundt-Nixon Bill.
    - Portaluppi - Prefabrication (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Includes Gropius' correspondence and statements regarding prefabrication, 1946-1963.
    - Pritchard, John (Jack), 1946-1961 (Box 11, Folder 8-13)
    - Pryzoda - Pusey (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Quebec, Place St. Cyrille Limitee (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Raabe - Reale Accademia D'Italia (Box 11, Folder 16)
      Includes Read, Sir Herbert, 1938, 1954-1968.
    - Redslob - Rickey (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Riegl, Alois (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Riemerschmid - Roth (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Royal Institute of British Architects (RIBA) Journal, 1934, 1936, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 20-22)
    - Royal Society of Arts, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 23)
      About the Gold Albert Medal.
    - Rubin - Russia (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Sabais - Schadlich (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Scharoun, Hans, 1964-1966 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Schawlinsky - Schiller (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Schinkel, Karl Friedrich (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Schlemmer - Schmidt, Pauli (Box 11, Folder 29)
      Includes Schlemmer, Tut, 1965, about Oskar Schlemmer; and Schmidt, Kurt, 1968.
    - Schneider - Selmanagic (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Sert, Jose Luis, 1939-1969 (Box 11, Folder 31-35)
    - Shanghai - Silber (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Simon - Soltan (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Sommerfield, Andrew, 1943-1949, 1964-1974 (Box 11, Folder 38-39)
    - Staber - Stevens (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - Sting, Hellmuth (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - Stout - Syrkus, Helena and Szymon (Box 11, Folder 42)
    - Tallahassee, Florida - TASK (Box 11, Folder 43)
    - Taunton Elementary School, Taunon, Massachusetts (Box 11, Folder 44)
    - Taut, Bruno and Max (Box 11, Folder 45)
    - The Architects Collaborative (TAC), 1945, 1961-1973 (Box 11, Folder 46-47)
    - Theater - Thiel (Box 11, Folder 48)
    - Thiersch - Thompson (Box 11, Folder 49)
    - Tiergarten, Berlin, Germany, circa 1931 (Box 11, Folder 50)
    - Tillich - Tupler (Box 11, Folder 51)
    - Uhlig, Klaus K. (Box 11, Folder 52)
    - United Nations Science and Culture Organization (UNESCO), 1947-1972 (Box 11, Folder 53-72)
      About the design and construction of UNESCO's headquarters in Paris including correspondence with Max Bill, Marcel Breuer, Wells Coates, Lucio Costa, Sigfried Giedion, Le Corbusier, Sven Markelius, Nervi, Ernesto Rogers, Eero Sarrinen, Jose Luis Sert, Zehrfuss, reports, and meeting minutes.
    - United Nations Headquarters, New York, 1946-1959 (Box 11, Folder 73)
    - Unwin - Utopia (Box 11, Folder 74)
    - Vagnetti - Van Voss (Box 11, Folder 75)
    - Waschmann, Konrad, 1962, undated (Box 11, Folder 76)
    - Wagner, Martin, 1940, 1981-1985 (Box 11, Folder 77-79)
    - Wagner - Waterstradt (Box 11, Folder 80)
      Includes Walden Pond Reservation, undated.
    - Weber - Weimar (Box 11, Folder 81)
    - Weissberger - Williams (Box 11, Folder 82)
      Includes Ise Gropius' correspondence with Wilder, Thornton, 1958.
    - Williams College - Windowless Factories (Box 11, Folder 83)
    - Wingler, Hans Maria, 1963-1979, undated (Box 11, Folder 84-85)
    - Wingler, Hans Maria and Heidi, 1980-1985 (Box 11, Folder 86)
    - Winston - Wright (Box 11, Folder 87)
      Includes Writings, 1967, 1969, undated; and Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1925, 1940.
    - Wurm - Zinn (Box 11, Folder 88)
      Includes Wurster, William, 1950-1953; and Zevi, Bruno, 1952, 1963-1965.
    - Oversized Map and Plat of Britz-Buckow-Rudow (BBR) (Box OV 23)
    - Oversized Plats, Am Lindenbaum Development Competition (Box OV 23)
    - Oversized Plat, A.P. Simon Housing Development Manchester, England (Box OV 23)
    - Drafts of Biography, circa 1972-1977, 1991; 13.3
      This subseries includes drafts of the two volume German edition, Der Mensch und sein Werk and a draft for volumes three and four (never published) as well as drafts of the English edition published posthumously, Walter Gropius An Illustrated Biography. All are in English.
      - Front Material, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Part 1: The Forge, A: Germany, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
      - Part 1: The Forge, B: Weimar, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
      - Part 1: The Forge, C: Dessau, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Part 1: The Forge, D: Berlin, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
      - Part 2: The Transition, A: Introduction to England, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Part 2: The Transition, B: Interlude in England, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
      - Part 3: The Fertile Ground, A: Changing United States, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Part 3: The Fertile Ground, B: Harvard University, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 13-14)
      - Part 3: The Fertile Ground, C: Emeritus Career, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Part 3: The Fertile Ground, C: Emeritus Career, and Epilogue, circa 1977 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Part 4: Attitudes and Principles, A: Introduction, circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - Part 4: Attitudes and Principles, B: Goals and Social Concerns, circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - Part 4: Attitudes and Principles, C: Education, circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 19)
      - Part 4: Attitudes and Principles, D: History, circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 20)
      - Part 4: Attitudes and Principles, E: Housing, Community, City, and Planning, circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 21)
      - Part 4: Attitudes and Principles, F: Responsibility, circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 22)
      - Part 4: Attitudes and Principles, G: Teamwork and the Collaborative Process, circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 23)
      - Part 4: Attitudes and Principles, H: Design, circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 24)
      - Part 5: The Works of Other Embodying Gropius' Principles, A: Introduction, circa 1972 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Part 5: The Works of Other Embodying Gropius' Principles, B: Students of the Bauhaus, circa 1972 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Part 5: The Works of Other Embodying Gropius' Principles, C: Harvard Graduates, circa 1972 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Part 5: The Works of Other Embodying Gropius' Principles, D: Others in the Professions and the Public, circa 1972 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Part 6: The Years to Come, A: Introduction and B: Consistency and New Directions, circa 1972 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Part 6: The Years to Come, C: Gropius - Symbol and Spokesman, circa 1972 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Part 6: The Years to Come, D: Predictions, circa 1972 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Prospectus, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Front Material, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Part 1: The Forge, A: Germany to 1918, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 10-12)
      - Part 1: The Forge, B: Weimar, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 13-15)
      - Part 1: The Forge, C: Bressau, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 16-17)
      - Part 1: The Forge, D: Berlin, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 18-20)
      - Part 2: The Transition, A: Introduction to England, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Part 2: The Transition, B: Interlude in England, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 2-4)
      - Part 3: The Fertile Ground, A: Changing United States, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Part 3: The Fertile Ground, B: Harvard University, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 6-8)
      - Part 3: The Fertile Ground, C: Emeritus Career, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 9-10)
      - Part 3: The Fertile Ground, Epilogue, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Part 4: Goals, Social Concerns, and Responsibility, A: Introduction, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Part 4: Goals, Social Concerns, and Responsibility, B: Goals and Social Principles, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Part 4: Goals, Social Concerns, and Responsibility, C: Responsibility, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - Part 5: Teamwork and the Collaborative Process, A: Introduction and B: In Education, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Part 5: Teamwork and the Collaborative Process, C: In Practice, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - Part 6: Eduation, A: Introduction and B: The Bauhaus, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 17)
      - Part 6: Education, C: The English Experience, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 18)
      - Part 6: Education, D: Harvard University, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 19)
      - Part 7: History, A: Introduction - Gropius' Heritage and B: Historical Influences, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 20)
      - Part 8: Design Principles, A: Introduction and B: Principles of Architecture, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 21)
      - Part 8: Design Principles, C: Architectural Works and Projects, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 22)
      - Part 8: Design Principles, D: Housing and Community, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 23)
      - Part 8: Design Principles, E?: Planning, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Part 8: Design Principles, F: Public Spaces, G: Landscape Architecture, H: Art and Art in Architecture, I: Interiors, Furniture, and Product Design (not included), and J: Parctice Management and Costs, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Part 9: The Works of Others, A: Introduction, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Part 9: The Works of Others, B: Students of the Bauhaus, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Part 9: The Works of Others, C: Harvard Graduates, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Part 9: The Works of Others, Others in the Professions and the Public, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
      - Part 10: The Years to Come, A: Introduction and B: Consistency and New Directions, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Part 10: The Years to Come, C: Gropius - Symbol and Spokesman, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 9-10)
      - Part 10: The Years to Come, D: Prediction, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 11-12)
      - Appendices, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 13-14)
      - Letters from Bullfinch Press Regarding Edited Manuscript, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 15)
      - 1st Edition, Forward, Preface, Prologue, and Chapter 1: The Forge, circa 1991 (Box 15, Folder 16)
      - 1st Edition, Chapter 2: The Young Architect, circa 1991 (Box 15, Folder 17)
      - 1st Edition, Chapter 3: Weimar and the Bauhaus, circa 1991 (Box 15, Folder 18-19)
      - 1st Edition, Chapter 4: The Dessau Bauhaus, circa 1991 (Box 15, Folder 20)
      - 1st Edition, Chapter 5: Berlin, circa 1991 (Box 15, Folder 21-22)
      - 1st Edition, Chapter 6: The Transition, circa 1991 (Box 15, Folder 23-24)
      - 1st Edition, Chapter 7: The Fertile Ground, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
      - 1st Edition, Chapter 8: Emeritus Career, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
      - 2nd Edition, Chapter 1: The Forge, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - 2nd Edition, Chapter 2: The Young Architect, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - 2nd Edition, Chapter 3:Weimar and the Bauhaus, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - 2nd Edition, Chapter 4: The Dessau Bauhaus, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - 2nd Edition, Chapter 5: Berlin, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - 2nd Edition, Chapter 6: The Transition, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - 2nd Edition, Chapter 7: The Fertile Ground, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Comments on the Biography, circa 1991, undated; 13.4
    These include the handwritten notes by Ise Gropius and Reginald Isaacs regarding the book drafts.
    - Notes, First Draft, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Notes, Second Draft, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Notes, Final Draft, circa 1991 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Comments by Ise Gropius, Parts 1-6, undated (Box 16, Folder 15-20)
    - Comments by Ise Gropius, 2nd Edition, Parts 4 and 6, undated (Box 16, Folder 21-22)
    - Editing Comments by Reginald Isaacs, Parts 1 and 2, undated (Box 16, Folder 23-24)
  - Publication Correspondence, 1969-1989; 13.5
    This subseries includes correspondence for the English and German editions of the biography with the Gerbruder Mann Verlag, Franziska P. Hosken, The M.I.T. Press, and the New York Graphic Society Ltd.
    - Correspondence Regarding English Edition of Biography, 1969-1989 (Box 16, Folder 25-32)
    - Correspondence Regarding German Edition of Biography, 1981-1983 (Box 16, Folder 33-38)
  - Photographs and Illustrations for the Biography, circa 1800s-1983, undated; 13.6
    This subseries contains the photographs and illustrations used in the published version of the biography Walter Gropius der Mensch und sein Werk. Walter Gropius biography, totaling 3 linear feet and including original and copy prints. At the beginning of the series are 3 folders containing a chart with the captions and credits for the materials. This, in concjunction with identification information on the materials themselves, serve as an excellent guide to the items.
    Some of the prints found here were taken by amateur photographers and belonged to Walter and Ise Gropius and others while most were taken by professionals. Isaacs' sons, Mark and Henry, also produced many images to aid in their fathers' research of Walter Gropius' building designs.
    The following Gropius family members, and other significant individuals, are depicted in photographs found throughout the subseries and particularly at the beginning:
    Walther Gropius (1848-1911): father
    Auguste Pauline Manon Scharnweber (1855-1933): mother
    Manon Gropius: sister
    Carl Ludwig Adolf Gropius (1819-1871): paternal grandfather
    Louise Honig Gropius (1821-1906): paternal grandmother
    Karl August Scharnweber: maternal grandfather
    Willy, Felix, and Erich Gropius: uncles
    Felicitas, Heidi, Conrad, and Werner: cousins
    (Johann) Carl Christian (1781-1854): great grandfather
    Wilhelm Ernst Gropius: great uncle
    Martin Karl Philipp Gropius (1824-1880): great uncle
    Georg Ludwig Gropius (1726-1784): great-great grandfather
    Dorothea Gropius (1739-1816): great-great grandmother
    Gabain, George (1763-1826) and Caroline (1769-1831): founders of the family silkworks
    The photographs and illustrations are arranged in rough chronological order according to the biography. An overview of the contents of each folder is provided in the container listing. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
    - 1-3: List of Captions and Credits, 1979-1983 (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
    - 4: Gropius signature; Gropius' principle; portraits of Gropius and Reginald Isaacs; bookplate by Gropius, circa 1903, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - 5: "Walter Gropius" caricature on tile, by Max Ernst; "Metallisches Fest;" Gropius "Fest;" family members and the Gabains, circa 1800s, 1929, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - 6: Schinkel, Karl Friedrich and 2 buildings designed by him; family members; Martin Karl Philipp Gropius and illustration for "Kladderadatsch," by him; Gropius brothers' diorama, circa 1800s, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - 7: Gropius as 2nd Lieutenant, Franco-Prussian War; family members; Gymnasium Liebniz, circa 1800s (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - 8: Gymnasium Kaiserin Augusta; Gymnasium Steglitz; Gropius; family members, circa 1800s, 1901 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - 9: Family members; Gross Schonfeld, estate of Carl Ludwig Adolf Gropius, Pomerania; principal estate workers of Gross Schonfeld, circa 1800s, 1906 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - 10: Hohenstein, estate of Felix Gropius, Kreis Deutsch Krone; Gropius; cousins; uncle Erich, circa 1800s-1900 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - 11: Kurnfurstendamm 25 (Now Hotel Am Zoo), Gropius' home; Gropius and friends; sister, circa 1890s-1903, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - 12: Gropius as Cadet, 15th Hussar Regiment Wandsbeck; Gropius and Loiuse Honig; Technische Hochschule, Munich; Konigliche Technische Hochschule, Berlin, 1902-1905 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - 13: Gropius, 1905; Gropius' term paper cover, -Viollet-le-Duc: Porportionen; term paper sketches and text, 1905, undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - 14: Granary (Kornspeicher), at Janikow; Erich Gropius house, Janikow; Metzner house, Dramburg; Farm worker's housing, Golzengot, 1903-1906 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - 15: Farm worker's housing, Janikow; site plan of Janikow housing; miscellaneous photos of Janikow (Warsaw), 1906-1907, undated (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - 16: Griesbach, Helmuth and Gropius in Spain, 1907 (Box 17, Folder 16)
      Two glass plate negatives housed in MGP 2.